Guide to the Women's Medical Society of New York State records, 1907-1972
Women's Medical Society of New York State records, 1907-1972
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Women's Medical Society of New York State records, 1907-1972.
2609
Women's Medical Society of New York State.
2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, newsletters, circular letters, minutes, reports, financial accounts, membership lists, a register, a scrapbook, a record book, clippings, photographs, and manuscript and printed miscellany.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence for the United Board for Christian Colleges in China; officials in medical schools in China, Korea, and India; student recipients of medical scholarships; and medical missionaries concerning their activities and the financial support which the Society gave to Christian women medical students in these countries; letters of women doctors concerning the business of the Society; and newsletters and circular letters of the Society, its Medical Education Committee, and various organizations and persons mentioned above. Also, minutes, reports, and financial accounts (1937-1966), membership lists, a register (1907-1956) including signatures of those attending various Society meetings, a scrapbook (1911-1953), a record book (1918-1952) consisting mainly of accounts of the Medical Education Committee, clippings, photographs, and manuscript and printed miscellany.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence for the United Board for Christian Colleges in China; officials in medical schools in China, Korea, and India; student recipients of medical scholarships; and medical missionaries concerning their activities and the financial support which the Society gave to Christian women medical students in these countries; letters of women doctors concerning the business of the Society; and newsletters and circular letters of the Society, its Medical Education Committee, and various organizations and persons mentioned above. Among the correspondents are Drs. Emily Dunning Barringer, Mary Theresa Greene, Rosetta Sherwood Hall, Jennie H. Harris, Harriet Hosmer, M. Pauline Jeffrey, and Sherwood Hall. Also, minutes, reports, and financial accounts (1937-1966), membership lists, a register (1907-1956) including signatures of those attending various Society meetings, a scrapbook (1911-1953), a record book (1918-1952) consisting mainly of accounts of the Medical Education Committee, clippings, photographs, and manuscript and printed miscellany.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Women's Medical Society of New York State.; Barringer, Emily Dunning, 1876-1961.; Greene, Mary Theresa.; Hall, Rosetta Sherwood.; Hall, Sherwood, 1893-; Harris, Jennie H.; Hosmer, Harriet.; Jeffrey, M. Pauline.; American Medical Women’s Association, Inc.; Medical Women’s International Association.; Pan American Medical Women’s Alliance.; United Board for Christian Colleges in China.; Women's Medical Society of New York. Medical Education Committee.
Subjects:
Medicine--Education.; Religion.; Women in medicine.; Women missionaries.; Women physicians.
Places:
China.; India.; Korea.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
This collection was reboxed at some point, combining 5 boxes of material into 3. Some of the items were mixed around and may not reflect their placement as described in this guide.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes 3 postcards of Castile Sanitarium run by Mary T. Greene, one of which was included with a letter to Harriett Northrup from Edward Greene, 1 unidentified photograph enclosed with November 28, 1957 letter from Pauline Jeffery, Kotagiri, Nilgiris, India, 1 photograph of Grace Ratnakumari included with undated letter to donor, photograph of Mary Susheela included with August 22, 1960 letter to donor, photograph of Grace Mathew included with September 4, 1961 letter to donor
  - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes copy of obituary of Irene A. Koeneke and article announcing her being awarded the University of Kansas Distinguished Service Citation
  - Wallin bequest, Mathilda K. Wallin Fund, 1955-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Copies of the will of Mathilda K. Wallin bequeathing $10,031.19 to the Women's Medical Society of New York State (will dated Nov. 15,1955, money received Sept. 22, 1959), correspondence relating to the settlement
- Series II. Other records and memorabilia
  - Women's Medical Society of New York membership list, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Women's Medical Society of New York list of names, ca. 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Women's Medical Society of New York list of names, membership list, ca. 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Women Physicians in Medical Directory of New York State for 1953, alphabetical list, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Women's Medical Society of New York State membership list and rosters, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Women's Medical Society of New York State list of officers, 1955, ca. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, agendas, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, agendas, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes form with biographical data for Medical Woman of the Year for 1954, Mary T. Greene, M.D.
  - Meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, agendas, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, agendas, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Includes newspaper clipping for Medical Woman of the Year, Dr. Margaret A. Baker
  - Meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, agendas, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes President's address February 13, 1966, newspaper clippings - obituaries, copy of certificate of recognition to Mrs. E. Snell Hall, press release - annual meeting
  - Medical Education Committee reports, bank books and receipts, 1937-1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Income tax exemption forms and correspondence, 1959-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 2 stamp seals Women's Medical Society, n.d.; MU-2053 (Box 3)
  - Small box containing 2 oval pins from the oval American Medical Women's Association and attached ribbons. Box says "Awards Branch 18 AMWA to Women's Medical Society of New York State"., n.d.; MU-2054 (Box 3)
- Series III. Manuscript and printed miscellany
  - Miscellaneous documents, ca. 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Includes brochures, sheet of seals for the eradication of tuberculosis from Ajmer, India, programs, blank birth certificate ballots for officers, articles from Medical Women's Journal
  - Miscellaneous documents, ca. 1960s (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Includes "Some Questions Commonly Asked Americans by People in the Soviet Union" and "Things to do and see in the USSR, Moscow, Leningrad by Information Center for American Travelers to the Soviet Union, "Abstracts of lectures to be presented at A Symposium on Sexual Problems in Clinical Practice, Washington, D.C., Saturday, November 5, 1966", Medicine at Work pamphlet, special issue pamphlet - Women in Health, November 1965 by pharmaceutical Manufacturers Association, brochures - AMDOC, Foreign Service Team Preceptorship Program, Women's National Safety Conference Citation Awards Program, The Elizabeth Blackwell Award by Hobart & William Smith College, program for Presentation of the Elizabeth Blackwell Award, Sunday, July 10, 1966
  - Warner, Dr. Marie P., ca. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Includes copy of obituary, curriculum vitaes, New York Infirmary reappointment form
  - Newsletters, 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, articles, 1935-1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes obituaries, awards, meetings, medical issues, women's medical practice, copy of "Women's Medical Society of New York State - A Brief History" by Isabella F. Borden, M.D. from Journal of the American Medical Women's Association volume 10, number 2, February 1955, "New York Medical Archives in Upstate Area" by Herbert Finch, Ph.D. from New York State Journal of Medicine, June 15, 1971
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, ca. 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Women Physicians' League constitution, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Volume labeled "Women's Medical Society Register", including signatures of those attending various Society meetings - acting and associate members, visitors, guests, 1907-1956 (Box 2)
  - Volume labeled "July 12, 1918 to Jan 1, 1952 Financial Record Book of Medical Education Committee", August 1917-February 1953 (Box 2)
    Includes membership list from April 28, 1913, mounted letters, excerpts from The Medical Women's Journal, and printed meeting materials
  - Scrapbook pages, ca. 1911-1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes magazine clippings, newspaper clippings, photograph of doctor at a mission, obituaries, Journal of the American Medical Women's Association Volume 5, March 1950, Number 3, October 1950, Number 10, and December 1950, Number 12, excerpts from Volume 7, June 1952, Number VI,2 postcards of first senior class W.M.I, Seoul, Korea, Tuberculosis Control in Two Lands [Korea and India] reprinted from World Outlook(367), sheet of seals for the eradication of tuberculosis in India and Pakistan, correspondence, list of names September 14, 1911, Castile, New York
  - Scrapbook, loose items, ca. 1911-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes copy of captioned newspaper photograph and original photograph of Dr. En-Mei Yui, Dr. Mary T. Greene, Dr,. Rosetta Sherwood Hall, and Dr. Marion Craig Potter, September 14,1911 library steps Castile, New York photograph of Dr. Katherine Mulhall, Dr. Jessica W. Findlay, Dr. Hatch, Dr. Sherman Riker, Dr. Mary Sloan, Dr. Helene Kuhlman, Dr. Dickinson, Dr. Christiana, Marian Greene, Dr. May Allen, Dr. Himmelsbock, Dr. Justin, Dr. Bennett, Dr. Mary Greene, Dr. Pierson, Dr. Louise Hurrell, and Dr. Clara March, 3 photographs - Liu Yui 1937, Dr. Y.T. Jiang and Dr. C.T. Chow 1937, Chang Hsiao Chang and Li Kwei Ling 1948, photographs of students Margaret Garrett and Kunjoonjamma Jacob, photograph of M.P. Jeffery, Edna Engle, and Nurse Kamalani, photograph K.M.F. chapel and dispensary building, 2 postcards of first senior class W.M.I, Seoul, Korea, resolution, ballots, meeting and annual dinner programs, Elizabeth Blackwell award pamphlet, correspondence, receipts, postcard new buildings of Ewha College, Seoul, Korea, postcard three senoir W.F.M.S. physicians of Korea - Dr. Rosetta Sherwood Helb, Dr. Mary Cutler, Dr. Stewart, printed photograph on Marian B. Hall, M.D., copy of picture and map of the new home of the W.M.I, Seoul,Korea with text in Korean, printed card including photograph from the Kotagiri Medical Fellowship, South India, photograph Dr. Rosetta Sherwood Hall, grand aunt of Rosetta Hall, magazine articles, obituaries, blank dues card, reports, committee members, letters in Korean, booklet - photographs of Greene Sanitarium and grounds, Castile, NY, World Service of the Methodist Episcopal Church missions program
  - Medical Women's Journal Volume 56, July 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Missing cover and pages 3-14
- Series IV. Medical Women's International Association (Association internationale des femmes médecins)
  - Medical Women's International Association Xth Extraordinary General Assembly, Sandefjord, Norway, June 29-July 3, 1964, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Program, statutes, agenda, financial reports, bound copy of Tenth General Assembly (Extraordinary) of the Medical Women's International Association M.W.I.A. lectures (received until June 14th)
  - Medical Women's International Association Tenth Congress, Rochester, New York and Niagara Falls, Ontario, Canada, July 9-15, 1966, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Programs, registrant list, workbook, remarks by Leo J. Gehrig, M.D., Deputy Surgeon General, Public Health Service, reports, agendas, registration and accommodation forms, opening address by Marion B. Folsom, former U.S. Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare, letter from Eric Northrup to Harriett Northrup
  - Medical Women's International Association newspaper clippings, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Medical Women's International Association XIIth Congress, Melborne, Australia, February 14-20, 1970, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Programs, agenda, reports, balance sheets, suggested rules of procedures at MWIA business meetings, agendas, reports
  - Medical Women's International Association XIIth Congress, Melborne, Australia, February 14-20, 1970, Scientific Papers, "The Health of Women in Industry" plastic comb bound volume, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Medical Women's International Association XIVth Congress, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, October 18-24,1974, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Program and supplement, report on family planning - supplement to proceedings
  - Genetics and Environmental Factors Which Affect Human Health, Proceedings, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, XIV Congress of Medical Women's International Association - M.W.I.A., October 13-18, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Medical Women's International Association, papers presented by members, ca. 1958-1974 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Includes "Family Planning in 1968 - A Basic Human Right" by Jessie Laird Brodie, M.D. prepared for XI Congress of the Pan-American Medical Women's Alliance, October 12-18, 1968, "Disorders of Sexual Behavior in Hospitalized Children with Primary Tb Complex" by Gilka Murillo de Guerra, M.D., "Charlataneria Medica - Los Curanderos" in Spanish, "Pelvic Phlebography in Benign Uterine Tumors" by Emilia Solani de Hard, "A Look at Medicine in Russia" by Alma D,. Morani, M.D., F.A.C.S, F.I.C.S. reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Women's Association, "Intestinal Parasitism - Report of an Interesting Case","Report: Care-Medico", "Pan American Medical Women's Alliance 1947 - 1967" by Jessie Laird Brodie, M.D., "Bronchopulmonary Malformations in Infancy" by Ana Amat, M.D., Bronchial Asthma in Infancy - Treatment with Ethylene Disulfonate" by Victoria Prieto de Manrique, M.D.,"Family Planning" by Aquilles J. Sobrero, M.D.
- Series V. Pan American Medical Women's Alliance
  - Pan American Medical Women's Alliance meetings, 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes information on X Congress, February 4-11, 1967 Lima, Peru, empty folder for 11th Congress, October 12-18, 1968, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,correspondence and schedule XVI Comgress, Santa Cruz, Bolivia, agenda September 24, 1973, bulletin for XII Congress 5-12 September,1971, Mexico, D.F., bulletin and program for XIII Congress 22-26 September, 1973, San Francisco, California [Spanish], program XV Congress September 1-6, 1977, San Juan, Puerto Rico, "The Comprehensive Community Mental Health Center, the New Trend in Psychiatry" by Martha Brunner-Orne, M.D., single sheet on Weber-Christian Syndrome by Rebeca Kuniyoshi, M.D.,"Bronchial Asthma in Infancy - Treatment with Ethylene Disulfonate
  - Pan American Medical Women's Alliance Newsletter, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Instituto de Puericultera, Universidade do Brasil, Rio de Janeiro, bound booklet, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series VI. American Medical Women's Association, Inc.
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes advertising discussions, organization profile, finances, Dr. Adelaide Ellsworth Weston Fund
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. correspondence - Harriett Northrup, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Includes duplicate certificate of membership in the American Women's Medical Association for branch no.18 New York State, Women's Medical Society of New York State annual meeting program from 1977 with notes written on back, copy of Women's Medical Society of New York State membership certificate for Alice W. Williams, 2 photographs of plaque "Given by the Women's Medical Society of New York State in memory of Dr. Lois J. Plummer of Buffalo, N.Y.", reports, correspondence regarding archival records housing
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. correspondence, memos, reports - Josephine Renshaw, President, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Includes finances, minutes, reports, list of Executive Board officers 1970
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. - Harriett Northrup, Treasurer files, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes Archives Committee reports, Liaison Committee report, reports, delegate certification, annual meeting schedules, correspondence, proposal, resolutions, press release, minutes, Constitution and Bylaws amended December 1967, brochures, President's report 1969, copy of finance newspaper clipping, memo, copies of "Tenth Anniversary Section - Looking Backward", April 1956 and "Women's Medical Society of New York State - A Brief History" by Isabella F. Borden, M.D., February 1955 from Journal of the American Medical Women's Association volume 10, number 2, February 1955, "New York Medical Archives in Upstate Area" by Herbert Finch, Ph.D. from New York State Journal of Medicine
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. audit, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. - Harriett Northrup, Treasurer files, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes agendas, minutes, account statements, disbursements, Resolutions 1960 - 1970, What's Happening in the AMWA July - September 1978, volume VI, number 3, Women's Medical Association of New York City newsletter, correspondence regarding travel agency arrangements The Woman Physician, American Medical Women's Asociation, Inc. Resolutions 1960 - 1970, correspondence, newsletters
  - American Medical Women's Association,Inc. credentials committee, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. pamphlets, 1940-1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes association yearbook 1940, official program from 1961 annual meeting in Ohio, Constitution and Bylaws adopted June 12, 1960, Constitution and Bylaws as amended to October, 1964
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. miscellaneous documents, ca. 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Includes pamphlets, official programs from annual meetings 1965, 1966, 1969, and 1970, resolutions, copies of magazine articles regarding 100th anniversary of Cornell University, "Statistics - Women and Medical School Application and Acceptances", Sophia J. Kleegman Professorship information, New Jersey Women's Association Branch 4, A.M.W.A. constitution and bylaws, oversize reprinted letter from Ida S. Scudder, on behaaf of the General Council of the Women's Missionary Medical College, to Lord Pentland, Governor of Madras in 1918, pamphlet "The Second Dr. Scudder of Vellore", "Via Transfusions Na Infancia" by Maria Piedade Calmon Cergne, brochure "Oral History Project on Women in Medicine", pamphlet "Pioneer-Pacesetter-Innovator; The Story of the Medical College of Pennsylvania, single page of bulletin on Edward G. Miner Library
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. interim meeting, Chicago, Illinois, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Includes Women's Medical Society of New York State Roster 1970 - 1972, agenda, appointments, annual meeting tentative program, reports, emeritus membership, excerpt on Louise Carpenter Gloeckner, M.D., vice president of the American Medical Association from Journal of the American Medical Women's Association volume 24, number 9, nominations for 1970 Elizabeth Blackwell Medal, Janet M. Glasgow Memorial Scholarship Fund, locales of interim and annual meetings 1958 - 1971, The National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc. news releases, blank questionnaire for promotion of women in policy-making positions, finances, membership figures 1960 - 1970
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. annual meeting, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. Medical Woman of the Year press releases, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Leona Baumgartner - New York State, Roberta Fenlon - Upper California, Thelma E. Frank - Texas, Mildred G. Gregory - New Jersey, Nelle S. Noble - Iowa, Elizabeth A. McGrew - Chicago, Dorothy M. Rogers - New Jersey, Esther H. Dale - Michigan, June Shafer - Washington, D.C., Carol G. Pryor - Georgia, Janet G. Travell - New York State
  - Report of a Conference on Meeting Medical Manpower Needs - The Fuller Utilization of the Woman Physician, Washington, D.C., January 12-13, 1968 (Box 2)
    Sponsored by American Medical Women's Association, The President's Study Group on Careers for Women, Women's Bureau, U.S> Department of Labor
  - Report to the University of Illinois College of Medicine Committee on Admissions from the Subcommittee on Women in Medicine, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania, 1950, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Includes pamphlet (1950) and article (1972)
  - American Medical Women's Association, Inc. folder and contents, A Symposium on Medicine in the Next 50 Years, Cicago, Illinois, Saturday, November 13, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Article clippings from Journal of the American Medical Women's Association, 1947-1952 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Journal of the American Medical Women's Association, 1951-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Volume 6, February 1951, Number 2
    Volume 17, August 1962, Number VIII
    Volume 21, October 1966, Mumber 10, M.W.I.A. Xth Congress
    M.W.I.A. X Congress Supplement
    Volume 22, Number 5, Pan American Medical Women's Alliance Xth Congress
    Volume 24, June 1969, Number 6, Papers from AMWA annual meeting December 1968 and papers presented at meeting of Branch 18 (New York State) February 1969
  - Women in Medicine - Official Quarterly of American Medical Women's Association, Inc., Number 71, January, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1964 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1965 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1966 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1967 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1969 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1970 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1971 (Box 3)
  - American Medical Women's Association Annual Reports, 1973 (Box 3)